Rahul, Ph.D.

Trafigura Global Services, Mumbai Email: r2rahul@uwaterloo.ca LinkedIn: https://in.linkedin.com/in/r2rahul/ Cell number: +919599109605

SUMMARY

I am an applied mathematician with extensive experience in developing mathematical models, university teaching, and data analysis. I am interested in designing and using efficient computational methods to analyze high throughput biological data, big data, and machine learning problems. Also, I am well versed in teaching methodologies and facilitating problem-solving sessions. As a sessional instructor at the University of Waterloo, I taught and developed exercises to stimulate deep thinking among my students.

POSITIONS

Manager
Trafigura Global Services, Mumbai, India

Associate
Blackrock Services India Pvt.Ltd, Gurgaon, India

Research Scientist
Data Science Practice, Impetus Infotech (India) Pvt. Ltd., Noida, India

Postdoctoral Research Fellow
Department of Biochemistry, McGill University, Montreal, Canada

Sessional Lecturer

Aug, 2018 - Present
Sep, 2015 - Aug, 2018

Jan, 2015 - Aug, 2015

Feb, 2014 - Dec, 2014

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy: Optimization, Control Theory, Systems Biology
Department of Applied Mathematics, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada

- Thesis: Kinetic Modeling of Pyruvate Recycling Pathways in Pancreatic β -Cells
- Relevant courses: Stochastic Process, Computational Biology, Numerical Analysis, Applied Functional Analysis, Academic Writing, Statistical Physics and other courses

Certificate in University Teaching: Teaching in University

2009-2011

Center of Teaching Excellence, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada

Department of Applied Mathematics, University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Canada

- Project Title: Using Wiki course page to enhance learning in a system biology course
- Workshops and Course works: Course Design, Understanding the Learner, Clickers for the Classroom, Academic Interview Skills, Evaluation of Teaching through trained observers, Midterm Evaluations

Master of Technology: Bioinformatics, Statistical learning, Stochastic Modelling 2006-2008 School of Computational and Integrative Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University, Delhi, India

- Thesis: Stochastic modeling of septation in Escherichia coli using Monte Carlo cell (MCELL)
- Relevant courses: Systems Biology, Computational Physics, Computational Methods for Sequence Analysis, Design and Analysis of Algorithms, Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery, Advanced Computational Methods in Bioinformatics, Introduction to Databases, and other courses

Master of Science: Control Theory, Statistics, Solar Cells

2003-2005

Department of Electronic Sciences, University of Delhi South Campus, Delhi, India

- o Thesis: Conducting Polymers and its Application to Solar Cells
- Relevant courses: Control Engineering, Signal and Systems, Modern Communication Systems, Advance Engineering Mathematics and other courses

Bachelor of Science: Electronic Sciences

2000-2003

Sri. Aurobindo College, Delhi University, Delhi, India

Rahul 2/4

CERTIFICATION

Massive Open Online Course (MOOC) Certificates:

 Coursera, Social and Economic Networks: Models and Analysis 	November, 2015
 edX, Scalable Machine Learning (Apache Spark) 	August, 2015
 Coursera, Learning How to Learn 	March, 2015
 Coursera, Linear and Integer Programming 	December, 2014
edX, LFS101x: Introduction to Linux	September, 2014
 Coursera, Reproducible Research 	July, 2014
 edX, Big Data and Social Physics 	May, 2014
 Stanford Online, Statistical Learning 	April, 2014
 edX, Effective Thinking Through Mathematics 	April, 2014
 edX, Introduction to Computer Science and Programming Using Python 	December, 2013
 Udacity, Statistics 	December, 2013
 Coursera, Computing for Data Analysis (R programming course) 	October, 2013
 Stanford Online, EDUC115N How to Learn Math 	September, 2013
 Coursera, Crafting an Effective Writer: Tools of the Trade 	June, 2013
Certificate in MATLAB, Indian Institute of Technology Kanpur	2005
Certificate in Japanese Language, Reiyukai	2004

ADDITIONAL TRAINING

Participated in the high performance computing training workshops, McGill University 2014

Introduction to Matlab Distributed Computing Server (MDCS)

Advanced MPI workshop

- Introduction to message passing interface (MPI)
- Introduction to open multi-processing (OpenMP)
- Introduction to high performance computing (HPC)

Participated in the learning to teach day conference, McGill University

2014
Attended graduate students skill-set workshops, McGill University

2014

- Strategies to support active and collaborative learning
- Clarifying expectations in graduate supervision
- Supervisory alliance
- Writing effective reference letters
- Evaluation and feedback in large classes using poster presentations
- Presentation skill workshop

· Fresentation skill workshop	
Participated in the math faculty teaching workshop, University of Waterloo	2013
Participated in the teaching squares, a faculty training program, University of Waterloo	2013

COMPUTER SKILLS

Programming Languages: MATLAB, MUPAD, Octave, R, C, Unix Shell Programming, FORTRAN 77, Python, IPython, Java Script, CSS, HTML, Markdown, ŁTFX

Software Tools: SBTOOLBOX2, SBPD, SUNDIALS, XPPAUT, MATCONT, MCELL, Celldesigner, Systems Biology Markup Language (SBML), Bioinformatics tools like BLAST, ClustalW, Visual Molecular Dynamics (VMD), *Version control system*: Git and SVN

Visualization Tools: Circos, Inkscape, Xfig, Blender 3D (Basic Knowledge)

Knowledge of:

- o Global sensitivity analysis and metabolic control analysis
- SPACE (Sparse Partial Correlation Estimation) and WGCNA (Weighted correlation network analysis) data analysis methods implemented in R programming environment non-linear equations

Educational Technologies: *iClickers* an audience response system, *Yed graph editor*, *Open-Sankore* an interactive whiteboard software, *Wiki* as a learning management system

SUPERVISORY EXPERIENCE

Undergraduate student, Department of Biochemistry, McGill University **Project:** Model curation of genome scale metabolic model of mouse

May, 2014 - August, 2014

Rahul 3/4

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Research Assistant, Postdoctoral fellow

2014

Department of Biochemistry, McGill University

 Project: Genome Scale Metabolic model for cancer cells using constraint based reconstruction and analysis (COBRA) method.

Research Assistant, Doctoral level

2008-2012

Department of Applied Mathematics, University of Waterloo

 Projects: Kinetic Modeling of Metabolic Pathways, Parameter Estimation and Global Sensitivity Analysis

Collaboration research with Parimal Samir in Andrew Link lab at Vanderbilt University School of Medicine 2013

Project: I analysed the quantitative proteomics and transcriptomics data of baker's yeast, Saccharomyces cerevisiae using SPACE (Sparse Partial Correlation Estimation) method implemented in R SPACE package. We identified functionally relevant hub proteins and modules in the co-expression network, which respond to differential signalling cues under different environmental conditions. The project codes are available on request.

Research Assistant, Master of Technology level

2007-2008

School of Computational and Integrative Sciences, Jawaharlal Nehru University

Project: Modelling of Distribution of Min proteins in daughter cells after cell division in Escherichia

Research Assistant, Master of Science level

2004-2005

Department of Electronic Sciences, University of Delhi South Campus

• Project: Design and analysis of conducting polymers based solar cells

Research Assistant, Master of Science level

May-September 2004

Indian Meteorological Department, Delhi

 Project: Analysis of upper atmosphere humidity data obtained through humidity sensors (Carbon Hygristors)

Research Assistant, Undergraduate Research Assistantship

2002-2003

Sri. Aurobindo College, Delhi University

o Project: 8085 based resistance and capacitance measurement meter

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Lecturer, University of Waterloo, Waterloo

2012-2013

- Calculus III for Honours Mathematics
- Calculus I for Engineers
- Calculus II for Sciences

Graduate Teaching Assistance, University of Waterloo, Waterloo

2008-2012

- Computational Cell Biology (Graduate Course)
- Environmental Informatics (Graduate Course)
- Calculus I, II, III for Engineers
- Introduction to differential equations
- o Linear Algebra I
- Calculus I, II, III for Honours Mathematics

SELECTED HONOURS AND AWARDS

International Doctoral Student Award, University of Waterloo	2008-2012
Mathematics Graduate Student Award, University of Waterloo	2008-2012
MITCAS student travel award to attend conference, University of Waterloo	2011
Department of Biotechnology Center of Excellence Award	2006-2008
Merit Certificate B.Sc(Hons) Electronic Sciences at Sri. Aurobindo College, Delhi University	2003
Qualified, Graduate Aptitude Test in Engineering (GATE)	2007
Cubicato Flacturation and Communication Fraction and CATE is announced by the discussion beauty	L L £ T l .

Subject: Electronics and Communication Engineering. GATE is conducted by Indian Institutes of Technology and Indian Institute of Sciences for admission to their graduate programs.

Rahul 4/4

DOCTORAL DISSERTATION WORK

Dissertation title: Kinetic modeling of pyruvate recycling pathways in pancreatic β -cells. Electronic copy of thesis work: https://uwspace.uwaterloo.ca/handle/10012/7044

PUBLICATIONS

Parimal Samir, **Rahul**, James C. Slaughter, and Andrew J. Link. Environmental Interactions and Epistasis Are Revealed in the Proteomic Responses to Complex Stimuli. *PLoS ONE*, 10(8):e0134099, August 2015

Parimal Samir, Christopher M. Browne, **Rahul**, Ming Sun, Bingxin Shen, Wen Li, Joachim Frank, and Andrew J. Link. Identification of changing ribosome protein compositions using mass spectrometry. *PROTEOMICS*, 18(20):1800217

Presentations

- Parimal Samir, Rahul, and Andrew Link. Quantitative proteomic analysis reveals environmental interaction and epistasis in the responses to complex stimuli in saccharomyces cerevisiae, 2015.
 63rd ASMS Conference on Mass Spectrometry and Allied Topics
- Rahul. A survey of wiki based collaborative learning environments for the interdisciplinary training of the students in maths and biology, 2012. Opportunities and New Directions Conference, Centre of Teaching Excellence, University of Waterloo
- \circ **Rahul**, Adam Stinchcombe, Jamie Joseph, and Brian Ingalls. Kinetic modelling of pyruvate recycling pathways in pancreatic β -cells., 2012. The 8th International Conference on Differential Equations and Dynamical Systems
- \circ Rahul, Adam Stinchcombe, Jamie Joseph, and Brian Ingalls. Dynamic modelling of metabolism in pancreatic β -cells., 2011. The International Conference on Applied Mathematics, Modelling and Computational Science (AMMCS)
- \circ **Rahul**, Adam Stinchcombe, Jamie Joseph, and Brian Ingalls. Dynamic modelling of metabolism in pancreatic β -cells, 2011. Graduate Student Conference

Posters

- Rahul, Fanny Dupuy, Sébastien Tabariès, Nicholas Bertos, Daina Z. Avizonis, Morag Park, Peter Siegel, and Uri D. Akavia. A computational method to integrate gene expression and metabolomics data to identify metabolic adaptations in cancer, 2014. Mechanisms & Models of Cancer Conference
- Rahul and Brian Ingalls. Optimal parameter estimation of kinetic models using the surrogatemodelling framework, 2013. RECOMB/ISCB Conference
- o **Rahul**, Adam Stinchcombe, Jamie Joseph, and Brian Ingalls. Dynamic modelling of pyruvate recycling pathways in pancreatic β-cells, 2012. 13th International Conference on System Biology, Toronto
- \circ **Rahul**, Adam Stinchcombe, Jamie Joseph, and Brian Ingalls. Dynamic modelling of metabolism in pancreatic β -cells, 2011. 7th International Congress on Industrial and Applied Mathematics ICIAM
- \circ **Rahul**, Adam Stinchcombe, Jamie Joseph, and Brian Ingalls. Dynamic modelling of metabolism in pancreatic β -cells, 2009. Chemical Biophysics Symposium

PROFESSIONAL INVOLVEMENT AND MEMBERSHIPS

Reviewed manuscript in the following journal:

Transactions on Biomedical Engineering, Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers Inc. (IEEE)
 Conference Attended:

1st Annual Montreal Postdoctoral Research Day, Montreal, Canada
 2014

International Biomedical Modelling School and Workshop, NCBS, Bangalore, India
 2008

Conference Volunteer: International Conference in Bioinformatics 2006, New Delhi, India

Professional memberships:

 Academic member International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB) 	2013-2015
 Student member Society for Industrial and Applied Mathematics (SIAM) 	2008-2012
 Student member International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB) 	2006-2008

REFERENCES Available on request.